Imagine you're an orthopedic surgeon, and a patient's file just lands on your desk from a general practitioner.
Right, just a standard intake.
Exactly.
And the intake notes read, upper limb injury requires surgery.
Which sounds totally fine, right?
Yeah, linguistically speaking, it's perfectly coherent.
I mean, you speak English, you understand those words.
There's absolutely zero breakdown in the transmission of the information.
But as a doctor, sitting there looking at that file, you are completely paralyzed.
You literally can't do your job.
Right.
Do you prep an operating room with, you know, microscopic tools for a highly delicate digital nerve repair on a finger?
Or do you pull out the heavy bone fixation plates for a shattered shoulder?
You have no idea.
The word was communicated perfectly, it was understood perfectly, but the system still failed catastrophically.
The vocabulary itself was a dead end.
Which is such a visceral way to look at it.
Yeah, so welcome to another deep dive.
Today, we're entirely rethinking the hidden architecture of the words you use every single day.
It's a massive shift.
I mean, it really shatters this illusion we all kind of carry around about what language actually is.
Right, because we have this comforting idea that our vocabulary is just like a giant warehouse of sticky notes.
Yeah, exactly.
You see a physical object, you stick a label on it.
Right.
Language, in that view, is just a descriptive tool for sharing information about the world as it currently exists.
But today, we're looking at this incredible June 2026 paper by independent researcher Flickshim.
Yeah, titled, Why Distinctions Survive?
A Reachability Theory of Lexical Preservation.
And this paper, it demands a paradigm shift.
It forces us to stop looking at language as just a tool for sharing information and start seeing it as an active instrument for navigating the future.
Navigating the future.
That shift from describing the present to navigating the future is the entire core of our mission today.
It really is.
We're going to answer a question that seems super simple on the surface, but gets incredibly deep the more you pull at it.
Which is, why do human languages merge some words together to save time, but then stubbornly refuse to merge others?
Exactly. And if you can understand the hidden mechanics behind that choice, you basically get a direct look at the secret rules governing human cognition.
It's like finding the source code.
Yeah. By the time we finish exploring this, you, listening right now, are going to look at the hyper-specific jargon you use at your job or in your hobbies in a completely different light.
You're going to realize you aren't just being pedantic when you correct someone's vocabulary.
No. You are actually protecting a future outcome.
So to really grasp the magnitude of what this paper accomplishes, we have to look at the system it's trying to replace, right?
We need the baseline.
Exactly. We have to establish how linguists, up until this point, believe languages organize their dictionaries.
And this revolves around a phenomenon known as collectification, right? Let's define that.
Yeah. So at its simplest, collectification is when a language uses a single word to express two completely different meanings or concepts.
And it happens constantly in every language on Earth.
All the time.
I mean, if you think about English, we use the word glass to refer to the material that makes up a window.
Right.
But we also use glass to refer to the cylindrical container you drink water out of.
We collectify the material and the object.
Exactly.
So what was the old theory explaining why we do this?
Well, the reigning theory was called the compression differentiation model.
Okay.
Specifically, Fliction's paper takes aim at a very prominent iteration of this model developed by Brock Hagen and colleagues.
And for years, this model was the absolute gold standard.
It was. It essentially treated the human brain like a highly efficient zip file.
A zip file. I love that.
Yeah. The foundational logic was that maintaining a massive vocabulary is cognitively expensive.
Your brain wants to conserve energy.
So it seeks an economy of effort by compressing multiple concepts into single words.
Right. Provided it doesn't cause too much confusion.
I was looking at the mathematical variables Brock Hagen used to build the zip file model.
Oh, yeah. Let's unpack those.
Okay. Let's unpack this because it basically boils down to a tug of war between two forces.
First, you have semantic similarity, which they denote as S.
Right. S for similarity.
And this is just mapping out how inherently related two concepts are in our mental framework.
Give you an example.
So the concepts of a river and a stream have extremely high semantic similarity.
They're both flowing bodies of water.
Right. They're physically and conceptually close.
Exactly. But the concepts of a river and a bicycle have almost zero similarity.
Makes sense.
And the second variable is contextual confusability, which they denote as C.
Okay. So how does C work?
This measures the environmental risk of a misunderstanding.
If I use the exact same word for two different concepts,
how likely is it that the listener will have no idea what I'm talking about based on the context of the room?
Or the rest of the sentence, right?
Exactly. So if we put those two variables together, the standard model's rule of thumb is essentially this...
If two concepts are highly similar and the context makes it blindingly obvious which one you mean,
a language will naturally compress them into one shared word.
You got it. That's the old model in a nutshell.
It makes me think of having a universal remote in your living room.
Oh, that's a good analogy.
Yeah. You have a television and you have a soundbar.
Functionally, they have high semantic similarity, right?
Yeah. They're both stationary electronic devices in your entertainment center.
And you control them from your couch.
But there's also very low contextual confusability.
Because you never really use the volume up button on the TV and the volume up button on the soundbar
for completely conflicting purposes at the exact same moment.
Exactly. So instead of keeping two separate clunky remotes on your coffee table, taking up physical space...
Or in the case of language, taking up cognitive space...
You just merge them into one single universal remote.
Why memorize two distinct phonetic forms when one merged form does the job perfectly well without causing any communicative breakdown?
Right.
According to Brock Hagen's model, when similarity is high and confusability is low, you get full collectification.
The words merge completely.
And if similarity is low, they stay distinct.
And this model wasn't just, you know, theoretical, right?
No. They tested it across nearly 2,000 different languages and the empirical fit was incredibly strong.
So the data seemed to prove that human language was just a simple efficiency engine.
Right. But, and this is a big but, the more I dug into the source material, the more it became clear that this perfect efficiency engine had some glaring structural flaws.
Yeah. Affliction points out that the standard model suffers from something called diachronic silence.
Which is such a great phrase.
It really is. It basically means the model is trapped in the present tense.
Exactly. It can look at a language as it exists right now, today, and accurately describe how words are grouped together.
But it has absolutely no ability to predict the future.
None at all. It can't tell you which of those merged words are going to stay merged, and which ones are going to inevitably shatter back into two separate words over the next few generations.
Yes. That is the first major crack in the foundation.
Taking a snapshot of a language today is like taking a photograph of a crowded intersection.
Oh, right. Because the photo tells you exactly where every car is at that specific millisecond.
But a still photograph cannot tell you the momentum of the cars.
You can't see the vectors.
Right. It can't tell you which two cars are on a trajectory to collide a second later, or which cars are safely passing through.
The standard model predicts which meaning should merge under current conditions, but it completely lacks any mechanism to distinguish between a harmless compression and a destructive compression.
And it doesn't just fail over time. It fails across different geographic regions, too.
Yeah. The paper brings up this problem of family-level heterogeneity.
Let's break that down.
So if you look at partial collectifications, where languages use a shared root word but maybe tack on a tiny prefix or suffix to tell them apart.
The old model totally breaks down.
Completely. Different language families handle these partial merges in wildly different, seemingly contradictory ways.
But instead of trying to figure out the underlying rule for why one culture splits a word and another culture murders it, the old model just kind of threw up its hands.
It essentially blamed it on a random historical noise.
Right. It treated a massive portion of human linguistic evolution as completely unpredictable.
Which brings us to the most damning flaw of all, the mathematical ghost.
The mathematical ghost. I love this part.
It's fascinating. In actual formula of the Brahegan model, there is a statistical interaction term between semantic similarity and contextual confusability.
Right. An empirical coefficient.
Yeah. When the original researchers ran their data through the computer, the formula wasn't predicting the real-world language structures accurately.
So what did they do?
They just added this statistical interaction term to the equation, and suddenly the graph fit the data beautifully.
But the problem is, they couldn't explain what that term represented in the real world.
Exactly. They basically injected a magic number into their math to make the theory work.
But if you ask them, hey, what is this number actually measuring in human behavior, they didn't have an answer.
It was a structural void. A placeholder for a phenomenon they could measure but couldn't understand.
And this is exactly where Flipschian steps in and fundamentally rewrites the rule.
Yeah. Because if the old model says we should merge words that are similar and not easily confused, and it works most of the time.
Do we have to look very closely at the moments where it spectacularly fails?
We have to figure out what that mathematical ghost actually is.
Right. If my universal remote works perfectly for the TV and the soundbar, I'm thrilled with the efficiency.
But at what precise moment do I realize that throwing away the original two remotes was actually a terrible, dangerous idea?
That is the perfect question, and it brings us to the central thesis of the paper and the introduction of a brand new variable.
Reachability divergence.
Yes. Mathematically, it is denoted in the paper as R sub theta d.
And this concept entirely replaces the old reliance on just similarity and confusability.
It does. Reachability divergence measures the degree to which two meanings, once you have distinguished them in your mind, open up entirely different future trajectories.
Okay. Whenever we start throwing around terms like future trajectories and admissible future regions, it can start to sound, you know, a bit like abstract science fiction.
It sounds a little sci-fi, yeah.
But the paper grounds this in incredibly practical daily reality.
Let's break down domain theta, the theta in the equation.
That just refers to a specific sphere of human activity, right?
Exactly. A domain could be anything from casual conversation over coffee to high-stakes aviation mechanics to culinary arts.
Let's use a kitchen example.
Okay, let's do it.
If you are a chef, your domain theta is the culinary environment.
And the future space in that domain is the massive set of all possible outcomes, right?
Yeah, all the physical actions, inferences, and potential errors you can make while cooking.
So chopping vegetables perfectly, burning the garlic, plating the dish, setting the kitchen on fire, those are all potential futures sitting out there in the space.
Correct. Now, the crucial concept here is the admissible future region.
Admissible future region. Okay, what is that?
For any specific word you use in that kitchen, the admissible future region is the narrow subset of those possible futures that actually lead to success.
So if the head chef yells, whisk, the admissible future is you picking up a wired tool and aerating a liquid.
Right. If you grab a knife and start chopping, you have exited the admissible future region. You have failed.
And this is where affliction draws a massive, brilliant line in the sand.
Yeah, reachability divergence is entirely logically independent of contextual confusability.
This is the critical dissociation, right?
It is. The risk of someone misunderstanding your word right now in the present moment has absolutely nothing to do with whether the word you chose strips away the specific details needed to take the correct action five steps down the road.
Let's ground this in the paper's prime example because this is where the theory totally clicked into place for me.
The hand versus arm example.
Yes. The concepts of hand versus arm.
If we look at general everyday vocabulary, these two concepts are heavily collectified across the globe.
They really are. Mandarin Chinese uses the single word shnei to cover the entire hand and arm.
And Swahili uses the word makono.
Arabic historically uses yad for the whole upper limb.
Why? Because they perfectly fit the old model.
Right. They have incredibly high semantic similarity.
They are physically connected body parts.
And in everyday life, they have virtually zero contextual confusability.
Exactly. If you are walking down the street with a friend who speaks Mandarin and they clutch their wrists and say,
my shang hurts, there is no communicative failure.
You completely understand they are experiencing pain in their upper limb.
The context, their body language, the casual setting, it makes the message perfectly clear.
The old model looks at that and says, see? High similarity, low confusability.
Therefore, the words merge. The system works.
But then fliction applies reachability divergence to a specific high stakes domain theta.
Surgical planning.
Which goes back to our opening scenario with the orthopedic surgeon.
Right. In a written medical referral, there is no physical pointing. There is no body language.
But more profoundly, even if the receiving specialist perfectly understands the general area of the injury based on the patient's history,
The future actions required to fix a hand versus an arm are violently divergent.
And this is the crux of reachability divergence.
Hand surgery dictates an admissible future of digital nerve repair, microscopic tendon reconstruction,
and highly specialized fine motor rehabilitation.
Whereas arm surgery dictates an entirely different admissible future.
Heavy orthopedic bone fixation, rotator cuff repair, gross motor shoulder rehabilitation.
The physical pathways to success literally do not overlap.
They don't.
You know, I found myself wanting to challenge this when I first read it.
Really? How so?
Well, I thought, wait a minute. If I tell a medical specialist, my arm hurts,
aren't I just passing them a packet of information? I'm simply describing a state of the physical world.
Right. Just describing the present.
Yeah. So how does my purely descriptive noun somehow dictate a future space?
Yes. It's a very natural pushback, but it conflates two totally different types of failure.
Yeah.
What's fascinating here is you have to separate communicative failure from navigational failure.
What's the difference?
Communicative failure is simple.
Did the receiver understand the definition of the word you transmitted?
Right.
But navigational failure asks a much more demanding question.
Does the word you successfully transmitted contain enough structural resolution to allow the receiver to physically execute the correct next action?
Oh, wow. It's the difference between hearing the music and knowing how to play the notes.
Exactly.
In a hospital system, if the administrative database uses a single merged word for hand and arm,
a routing clerk reading a patient's file might perfectly understand that the patient has an upper limb trauma.
So the communication was 100% successful.
The clerk knows exactly what the word means.
But because that merged word lacks the structural distinction between hand and arm,
the clerk cannot navigate the hospital's future.
Right. They don't know whether to route the patient to the microscopic nerve specialist or the heavy bone orthopedist.
And that is a catastrophe.
The system fails, not because someone was confused, but because the linguistic representation itself was a dead end.
Which brings us to the rigorous mechanics of what Fliction formally defines as navigational collapse.
Let's dive deep into the mechanics of this collapse.
Yeah.
Because the paper outlines a formal proof for this, which revolves around the concept of a representational bottleneck.
Yes. Theorem 1.
I want to spend some real time here, because this is where the paper stops being just a linguistic observation
and starts feeling like systems engineering.
It really does.
The bottleneck isn't human intelligence.
The bottleneck isn't the skill of the doctor or the reading comprehension of the clerk.
The bottleneck is the actual physical work.
Precisely.
In complex distributed systems, like a modern hospital, a legal network, or a massive supply chain,
you cannot rely on face-to-face context.
You can't just point at things.
No. Information has to be abstracted into written words, stored in databases,
and transmitted across time and space to people who have never met you.
And in those scenarios, the entire reality of the situation is forced through the representational
bottleneck of the vocabulary.
The word is the only thing that survives the transit.
Right. And if that single merged word has collapsed, a vital physical distinction just
to save a tiny bit of cognitive space, the downstream recipient is functionally blind.
Let me try a non-medical analogy to make sure I'm mapping this correctly.
Go for it.
Let's say I'm going out of town for a month and I hire a pet sitter.
Okay.
I leave a very brief note on the counter that just says, feed the pet.
Simple enough.
Now, linguistically, there is no confusability.
The pet sitter knows what the English word pet means.
The communication is flawless.
But that word is a severe representational bottleneck.
Yes.
It successfully communicates the general domain of animal husbandry,
but it totally obliterates the required future actions.
Because your note doesn't tell the sitter if they're supposed to open a can of wet food
for an elderly golden retriever.
Or if they're supposed to use tongs to drop a live mouse into a terrarium for a python.
That is an outstanding illustration of navigational collapse.
It makes it so clear.
The word pet is a highly compressed, merged form.
It groups together dogs, cats, snakes, birds, and hamsters based on their high semantic similarity.
Right.
They're all domesticated companion animals.
In a casual conversation at a coffee shop saying, I have to go feed my pet,
works perfectly because the listener doesn't need to take any action.
The reachability divergence in the coffee shop domain is basically zero.
Exactly.
Because your friend at the coffee shop isn't coming to your house to do the feeding.
Right.
But the moment you enter the domain of the pet sitter, the reachability divergence spikes to maximum.
Because the physical reality of feeding a golden retriever versus feeding a python
involved entirely different tools, different timing, different safety protocols.
The future actions are entirely blocked by your choice to use a generic, merged word.
And this leads directly into the paper's mathematical proof of stability, the second theorem.
Yes.
The math of fragmentation.
How does the paper define a stable word versus an unstable word?
Well, the author proves that a merged word, a clexification, is only stable within a language
if it preserves the full union of all admissible futures.
Okay, let's translate.
Preserves the full union of all admissible futures into practical reality.
It means that if you're going to take two distinct concepts and smash them together into
one word to save brain space, that new single word must still allow you to successfully perform
every single action you could have performed when you had two separate words.
Got it.
And if it doesn't?
If the merged word causes any reachability loss, meaning it closes off necessary future
actions, exactly like your pet example closed off the specific feeding protocols, then that
word is fundamentally broken.
It is a navigational hazard.
Exactly.
And the paper makes a diachronic prediction here, a prediction about the momentum of language
over time.
Right.
Getting back to the vectors.
Yes.
It states that words carrying a high reachability loss don't just eventually fragment.
They fragment at an accelerated rate.
So the speed at which a language invents new words or splits old ones is directly proportional
to how much physical navigational damage the old merged word was causing the community.
That is the elegance of the diachronic model.
If you leave that note saying, feed the pet, your pet sitter isn't just going to sit there.
No.
They're going to immediately call my phone and demand that I fragment my language.
Exactly.
They will force you to use a more precise term, feed the dog or feed the snake, because
the navigational loss of the word pet in that specific environment is intolerable.
The system will forcefully demand a linguistic repair.
But this opens up a fascinating economic question.
If human languages are constantly facing these micro threats of navigational collapse in all
these different specialized domains, how do they fix it without completely bankrupting
our cognitive limits?
Right.
Because if we had to invent a brand new, completely unique word every single time a tiny physical
distinction mattered, our dictionaries would be millions of words long.
We wouldn't be able to memorize them all.
You're hitting on the core of the economics of linguistic repair, which is the third theorem
Flixian formalizes mathematically in the paper.
Okay.
It is a constant, brutal balancing act between two competing costs.
On one side, you have the formal complexity cost.
The formal complexity cost.
So this is the cognitive price tag of fixing language.
Yes.
Creating an entirely new word from scratch is incredibly expensive.
You have to invent a new phonetic sound, establish its spelling, memorize its definition,
and then culturally transmit it to thousands or millions of other speakers so they all agree
on what it means.
That is a massive undertaking.
And on the other side of the ledger.
On the other side, you have the reachability loss.
This is the physical price tag of navigating the world incorrectly.
Right.
This is the cost of the surgeon operating on the wrong limb.
Or the bridge collapsing because the engineer used the wrong material.
Or the python starving because the sitter bought dog food.
Exactly.
So the language community is constantly weighing the brainpower cost of inventing a new word
against the real-world danger of keeping an old merged word.
How does the math resolve that trade-off?
What is the cheapest, most effective way to fix a broken word?
The mathematically optimal solution, and the one we see languages naturally adopt over centuries,
is partial collectification.
Partial collectification.
So we don't throw away the old word.
No.
You keep the shared root, which preserves the massive cognitive investment the community
has already made in learning it.
But you tack on a tiny, low-cost residual marker.
Right.
A prefix, a suffix, a slight tone shift, just enough to restore the missing distinction.
The paper provides a rigorous mathematical proof showing that full differentiation,
inventing a totally separate word, is strictly dominated by partial differentiation.
Because inventing a totally new word wastes the compression investment.
I love the example the paper uses to illustrate this because it transitions us from bodily injuries
into the environment.
Ah, the wood versus tree example.
Yes.
The distinction between wood and tree.
In Arabic, there is a general word, shajara, which in everyday casual discourse covers both
the concept of the living, breathing organism with leaves, and the dead material you chop up to build a fire.
In casual life, they are fully colexified.
And in the domain of a typical household, that full colexification is perfectly stable.
If you tell someone to go look at the shajara in the yard, they look at the living tree.
If you tell them to put more shajara in the oven, they grab a log.
The futures are easily accessible, and they don't violently conflict.
But then the paper introduces Proposition 4, domain divergence.
And this blew my mind.
It's so cool.
It proves that a word can be perfectly safe in your living room, but a lethal navigational
hazard at your job.
Let's look at the domains of forestry management, industrial logging, or environmental ecology.
In those highly specialized, high-stakes arenas, the concepts of tree and wood absolutely must
diverge.
The admissible futures in forestry are mutually exclusive.
Right.
Because the concept of tree controls futures, related to biodiversity assessments, monitoring
soil health, tracking carbon sequestration, and planning multi-decade replanting schedules.
And you cannot do those things with a dead log.
Exactly.
The concept of wood controls entirely different futures, calculating kimber yields, managing
kiln drying schedules, structural load testing, and negotiating board foot pricing on the
commodities market.
If an international logging conglomerate tries to manage its supply chain using a database
that only has one single word for both the living organism and the harvested material,
their entire logistical system collapses.
They wouldn't know if they were buying a protected forest or a stack of 2x4s.
And this is where Fliction's theory leaves the realm of grammar and becomes a theory of
human knowledge generation.
This proposition literally predicts the emergence of technical vocabularies.
It explains, at a fundamental mathematical level, why scientific nomenclature exists, why legal
terminology is so dense, why programming languages have such strict syntax.
Jargon.
We are talking about the birth of jargon.
Exactly.
We often complain about jargon.
We think it's just professionals being elitist or trying to sound smarter than everyone else.
Or intentionally walling off their club.
But from the perspective of reachability theory, jargon is an admissibility restoring repair.
It is a necessary evolutionary step to prevent domain-specific disasters.
Here's where it gets really interesting for anyone listening.
Yeah.
I really want you listening right now to apply this to your own life.
Think about the hyper-specific, nuanced words you use at your job or in your deepest hobbies.
Think about the times you find yourself getting incredibly pedantic when a friend or a spouse
misuses a term that you work with every day.
You aren't just being annoying.
You are subconsciously feeling the friction of navigational loss.
You are using jargon as a protective tool to keep your specialized future space open.
When a civil engineer furiously insists on the mathematical difference between stress
and strain, they are not being pedantic about dictionary definitions.
No.
They are protecting human lives.
Because stress is the internal force applied to a material, and strain is the physical
deformation that results from that force.
If those two concepts collapse back into a single colloquial word in an architectural blueprint,
a structural failure isn't just possible, it's guaranteed.
The bridge falls down.
Exactly.
When a prosecutor insists on the absolute legal boundary between murder and manslaughter,
they are preserving the entire architecture of the justice system.
This system demands that the distinction survives because the loss of that distinction is action
theoretically inadmissible.
So we have this sweeping, elegant theory.
We've gone from universal remotes to surgical pathways to the logging industry.
But, you know, theories are just stories until you test them.
I spent a lot of time looking at Section 7 of the source material, where Affliction actually
puts this entire framework to the test against the real-world cross-linguistic databases.
Because this isn't just a thought experiment.
No.
It is heavily empirical.
The paper includes a pilot estimation using 20 specific meaning pairs drawn from massive
standardized databases like Lexibank and CLICS.
For those unfamiliar, databases like CLICS, the Database of Cross-Linguistic Collectifications,
map out how thousands of concepts are linked together across thousands of languages.
It is literally a treasure trove of human cognitive mapping.
Affliction used this data to see if reachability divergence actually predicts the real structure
of human language better than Brock Hagen's old similarity confusability model.
And the ultimate battleground for this test, the place where the old theory and the new
theory go head-to-head, is what the paper designates as the HLH cell.
Yes, the HLH matrix cell.
It stands for high semantic similarity, low contextual confusability, but high reachability
divergence.
This is the perfect trap for the old model.
It really is.
Because if you have two concepts with high similarity and low confusability, Brock Hagen's old model
is screaming at the top of its lungs.
These words must merge.
They are the perfect ideal candidates for full, harmless compression.
But Flixen's new theory steps in and says, wait, look at the third variable.
They have high reachability divergence.
Right.
If you merge them, you might save some cognitive space, but you will cause catastrophic navigational
collapse in specialized domains.
Therefore, they will resist merging.
They will fight to stay distinct.
Or at most, they will only partially colexify.
So we look at the data to see who wins.
The paper highlights several core pairs from this exact HLH cell.
We already talked about wood and tree and hand and arm.
But there's also skin and blicus.
Oh yeah.
Very high similarity.
They are both the outer protective layer of a living organism.
Very low confusability.
If you point at a tree and say skin, people know what you mean.
The old model says they should merge.
Another pair is tongue and language.
Pi similarity, low confusability.
And when you look at the Lexibank and CLICS data across thousands of languages, the results
are definitive.
These specific pairs do violently resist full merging across unrelated language families.
Despite being highly similar and rarely confusable in context, human cultures all over the
globe stubbornly refuse to fully collapse them.
They either show up as partial colexifications, sharing a root but carrying a distinct marker,
or they remain entirely separate words.
The old theory predicts they should all be seamlessly merged.
The old theory is empirically wrong.
To really drive this home and show the contrast, I want to look at a pair of words from the data
that acts as a control group, finger and toe.
That is a phenomenal contrast pair.
Because finger and toe possess high semantic similarity.
They are structurally identical concepts.
Digits located at the terminal ends of human limbs.
They possess low contextual confusability.
If you are walking barefoot and stub your foot on a rock and you yell, I stubbed my digit,
the environmental context makes it overwhelmingly obvious you mean your toe, not your finger.
So Brockhagen's old model says they are prime candidates for merging.
And the brilliant thing is they actually do merge.
We see it everywhere.
In Spanish, the word is dito for both.
You just say dito of the hand or dito of the foot.
In Russian, the word is pallic for both.
The old model looks at that and takes a victory lap.
But the new question is, why do finger and toe happily merge in Spanish and Russian,
while hand and arm violently resist merging all over the world?
Because of reachability divergence.
Right.
For finger and toe, the reachability divergence is fundamentally low, even in specialized domains.
Think back to the medical futures.
Okay, if you severely injure a finger or you severely injure a toe.
The downstream orthopedic futures, the actual physical actions required by a medical professional
to fix a digit injury, are virtually identical.
You splint it, you tape it, you rest it, you might set a tiny bone.
The medical futures do not violently diverge the way microscopic hand nerve surgery diverges
from heavy shoulder reconstruction.
That is incredible.
Because the medical futures are structurally parallel, the merged word dito is perfectly
stable.
The compression causes absolutely no navigational loss, even for a doctor.
Exactly.
The physical reality of human anatomy dictates the grammatical reality of the language.
The words map to the physical futures.
And this leads to what I think is the most satisfying intellectual payoff in the entire paper.
Oh, the projection theorem.
Yes.
It's the moment where Flicksheim doesn't just debunk the old model, but actually explains
why the old model seemed to work for so long.
It is a moment of pure mathematical elegance.
We talked earlier about that mathematical ghost, the unexplained statistical interaction
term that Brock Higgins' team had to invent to make their equation fit the data.
Right.
In the projection theorem, Flicksheim mathematically proves that this ghost was actually just the
shadow of reachability divergence all along.
I had to read that proof three times because it was so fascinating.
You're saying the linguists who built the old model saw the footprint of this massive phenomenon
in their data, but they had no idea what kind of animal had left the footprint.
That is precisely what happened.
The old model's math was surprisingly accurate because, without knowing it, it was capturing
the projection of reachability divergence onto the flat plane of similarity and confusability.
The mathematical equation intrinsically knew there was a missing dimension, a third axis
of reality, even if the human linguists looking at the equation didn't.
By formalizing reachability divergence, Flicksheim didn't just break the old model, they solved
its greatest mystery.
They explained exactly why the old model almost worked.
So, knowing all this, how do we move forward?
If we completely accept this new paradigm, how do future linguists and data scientists actually
operationalize it?
How do you measure it?
Yeah, how do you mathematically measure something as vast and abstract as future space?
Because it sounds like you would need a crystal ball.
The paper is actually very rigorous about this in the methodology sections.
We don't need a crystal ball.
We need data trails.
Data trails.
Flicksheim outlines several concrete methods for operationalizing reachability divergence.
The most compelling is the use of action consequence corpora.
Break that down for me.
What does an action consequence corpus actually look like in practice?
It is essentially mining massive structured data sets where specific written words directly
dictate subsequent physical actions.
Like what?
Think about incredibly detailed medical billing databases.
You have a massive column of diagnosis codes.
Those are the words.
Okay.
And they are directly linked to subsequent billing codes for procedures and medications.
Those are the physical actions.
Ah.
By feeding this into an algorithm, you can mathematically measure the divergence between the action distributions.
If word A always leads to action path X and word B always leads to action path Y, you have quantified the reachability divergence.
That makes total sense.
Right.
You just follow the paper trail of human action.
But what about domains that don't have perfect billing codes?
The paper suggests prompting large language models to simulate decision trees.
Using AI.
Right.
You can constrain an AI to a highly specific domain, say, deep sea welding.
You ask the AI, given that the environmental state is X, map out the next 10 necessary physical steps to prevent a breach.
And then you do the exact same prompt for state Y.
You measure the topological gap between the AI's generated decision trees.
And if you don't trust AI, you can use structured expert elicitation.
Sitting down with the actual humans who do the work.
Exactly.
You sit down with a veteran surgeon, a master botanist, a senior aviation mechanic, or a trial lawyer, and you force them to meticulously map out their operational workflows.
You isolate the exact vocabulary they use at the crucial forks in their decision trees.
So this isn't just a philosophical argument.
This is a fully testable, robust research program that could map the entire architecture of human knowledge.
Which brings us to the grand conclusion of this deep dive.
We have covered an immense amount of ground today.
We really have.
We've deconstructed the zip file theory of the brain, explored the hidden dangers of univercal remotes and generic pet sitters, mapped the divergence of Arabic forestry terms,
and proved that a mathematical ghost was actually the shadow of the future.
It's a lot to take in.
It is.
So what does this ultimately mean for the listener?
It means we must fundamentally redefine what language is.
The ultimate overarching thesis of this paper is that human language is not, and has never been,
just a passive system for balancing communicative efficiency against present tense ambiguity.
That dictionary view of language is dead.
It is a profound shift in perspective.
The new view, proven mathematically and empirically, is that language is an active system for preserving the distinctions required to keep a community's future navigable.
Compression determines if meanings can merge without confusing people today.
Reachability determines if those meanings can remain merged without destroying the systems of tomorrow.
Lexical distinctions are not just tags we slap on objects.
They are the active steering wheels of human civilization.
The words you choose aren't just descriptions of the world as it currently sits.
They are the literal tracks you are laying down for the train of reality to run on.
And if you collapse the wrong distinction, the train derails.
Which forces us to reconsider how we view the loss of knowledge itself.
When a culture or a specialized community loses a fine-grained distinction in its vocabulary, it doesn't just become slightly less precise.
No, it loses the representational capacity to route physical reality to the correct outcome.
The distinction survives across centuries because its loss is action theoretically inadmissible.
It's quite literally a matter of survival.
Which brings me to a final provocative thought I want to leave you with.
Okay, let's hear it.
Think about a recent moment where you found yourself getting incredibly frustrated.
Maybe even irrationally angry.
Because someone confused two terms that seemed totally interchangeable to them, but were worlds apart to you.
Like a graphic designer losing their mind when a client calls a specific font a typeface.
Exactly.
Was your frustration in that moment actually just about grammar?
Were you just trying to be a dictionary police officer?
Or, armed with everything we've learned today, were you subconsciously sensing a massive navigational collapse?
What specific disastrous future, a ruined design, a failed project, a miscommunicated brand, were you desperately trying to prevent by insisting on that specific word?
It's a powerful realization.
The next time you catch yourself being a stickler for hyper-specific vocabulary, don't feel bad about it.
You aren't just correcting someone's grammar.
You are actively fighting to keep the future navigable.
Keep the tracks clear.
Thank you so much for taking this journey into the architecture of words with us.
Go take a hard look at your own daily jargon, and we'll catch you on the next deep dive.